Preliminary Inventory to the Wladyslaw Wszebor Kulski Papers, 1930-1984
Hoover Institution Archives
Wladyslaw Wszebor Kulski Papers,
1930-1984
92017
Kulski, Wladyslaw Wszebor, 1903-
8 manuscript boxes (3.3 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoirs, other speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, dispatches, legal and diplomatic agreements, and printed matter, relating to interwar Polish foreign relations; Polish participation in the League of Nations; Polish diplomacy during World War II, especially with regard to Great Britain; and postwar analysis of political conditions in Poland and Europe.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
Biographical/Historical Note
Polish diplomat; chief legal adviser, Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, 1936-1940; counsellor of embassy to Great Britain, 1940-1945; subsequently political scientist in the United States.
Access Points
Poland--Foreign relations.; League of Nations.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Poland--History--Occupation, 1939-1945.; Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych.; Poland--Foreign relations--Great Britain.; Great Britain--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poles--United States.; Poland--Politics and government--1945-1980.; Europe--Politics and government--1945-; Poland.; Great Britain.; United States.; Europe.; Diplomats--Poland.
Container List
- Files:
  - 1. W. Kulski: Typed manuscript of memoires in English (final text) (Box 1)
  - 2. Polish-Soviet Union diplomatic relationship during World War II -, 66 documents.
  - 3. Question of the border between Poland and Czechoslovakia -, 15 pieces.
  - 4. White Book of the Polish goverment in exile - typed manuscript.
  - 5. Comite Interallic pour L'Etude de L'Armistice, London 1942-43 and 1943-44 -, (two volumes).
  - 6. International agreements on river navigation (1918-39) -, 4 documents.
  - 7. Various letters -, 20 pieces.
  - 8. Political agreements between Poland and France or Great Britain -, 32 documents. (Box 2)
  - 9. Goals of World War II -, 52 documents.
  - 10. Speeches of W. Kulski -, 29 typed manuscripts.
  - 11. Polish-Soviet relationship during World War II -, 42 documents.
  - 12. Europe -, 10 pieces.
  - 13. International law on war and neutrality -, 1 piece. (Box 3)
  - 14. Varia -, 7 pieces.
  - 15. Situation of the Polish Goverment-in-Exile, immunitets -, 14 pieces.
  - 16. Dispute between Poland and France related to the Warsaw Electric Power Station.
  - 17. Diplomatic relations between Poland and Great Britain -, 9 documents.
  - 18. Propaganda during the II World War, Chatham House -, 11 pieces.
  - 19. Goals of World War II -, 19 pieces.
  - 20. U.S. Office of War Information, 1945 - 58 publications.
  - 21. Poland-Czechoslovakia -, 14 pieces.
  - 22. Relationship between Poland and Germany after World War II -several typed manuscripts by W. Kulski.
  - 23. Revievs for The Polish Review by W. Kulski -, 13 pieces. (Box 4)
  - 24. W. Kulski's documents related to the University of Alabama, letters from publishers - numerous documents.
  - 25. Poland-Soviet Union, 1941-45 -, 7 pieces.
  - 26. Negotiations for new organization of Europe before World War II -, 41 documents.
  - 27. Freedom of navigation in straits - 7 documents from before 1939.
  - 28. International agreements -, 11 documents.
  - 29. Personal matters of PV division of Polish Foreign Ministry before 1939 -, 30 documents.
  - 30. Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs -, 2 documents.
  - 31. Lituanian and Ukrainian matters during World War II -, 2 documents. (Box 5)
  - 32. Polish Ministry of Foreign Affairs (before 1939) - question of colonies and mandates.
  - 33. A question of the Polish-German border during theII World War -, 23 documents.
  - 34. Goals of World War II -, 13 documents.
  - 35. Polish-German negotiations on ethnic minorities before World War II -, 22 documents.
  - 36. Lithuanian problem (before 1939) -, 15 documents.
  - 37. The Geneve convention -, 11 documents.
  - 38. Antonina Kulska (a wife of Dr. Kulski) - public speeches during World War II /woman organizations in Great Britain, letters -, many pieces. (Box 6)
  - 39. A problem of German transit through Poland before September 1939 -, 3 documents.
  - 40. Documents from November/December 1939 -, 12 pieces.
  - 41. Miscellanous documents 1939-45 (the Polish Goverment-in-Exile) -, 20 pieces.
  - 42. Polish-Soviet relationship -, 55 documents.
  - 43. Polish-Czechooslovakian relationship during 1939-45 -, 36 documents.
  - 44. The League of Nations -, 18 publications and 9 documents.
  - 45. Letters by W. Kulski - 4 (Box 7)
  - 46. Correspondence of W. Kulski with the Rockefeller Fund -, 7 letters.
  - 47. W. Kulski: Soviet Union in World Affairs', 2nd edition - typed manuscript.
  - 48. Kultura the Polish magazine in Paris - letters and typed manuscript by W. Kulski.
  - 49. Poland-DDR relationship - typed manuscripts and paper clippings.
  - 50. Varia - few typed manuscripts by W. Kulski.
  - 51. World War II - clippings from Polish newspapers.
  - 52. Numerous pieces related to sojourn of W. Kulski in England and U.S.A.
  - 53. Diplomatic relationship between Poland and Great Britain and France in 1939 -, 48 documents.
  - 54. Polish Government decrees, 1940.
  - 55. Danzing (Odansk) question before September/1939 -, 31 documents.
  - 56. Polish Government (varia 1938/39) -, 15 pieces.
  - 57. Materials related to the book by W. Kulski Germany and Poland: from War to Peaceful Relations, Syracuse Univ. Press, 1976 (reviews and letters). (Box 8)
  - 58. Materials related to a book by W. Kulski The Soviet Union in World Affairs: a Documented Analysis, 1964-1972, Syracuse Univ. Press, 1973 (mostly reviews).
  - 59 Great Britain and Europe - 4 typed manuscripts by W. Kulski.
  - 60. Speeches of Antonina Kulski to woman organizations during II World War II.
  - 61. Antonina Kulski: a copy of master thesis The last political writing of J.J. Rousseau, University of Alabama, 1952.
  - 62. Antonina Kulski's notebook (notes on Voltaire).